<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
<channel>
<title>OpTiMSoC</title>
<description>OpTiMSoC project blog</description>
<link>http://www.optimsoc.org/blog</link>
<atom:link href="http://www.optimsoc.org/blog/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />

<item>
<title>Many New Ideas from ORCONF</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Every autumn the community around the OpenRISC processor meets somewhere to 
discuss the current status of the project, to exchange ideas with other 
free/open hardware projects, and to discuss future directions. This year the 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://orconf.org&quot;&gt;OpenRISC Conference &amp;ldquo;ORCONF&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; was held at TUM in Munich and 
attracted around 40 people from all over Europe and the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The OpenRISC processor implementation &amp;ldquo;mor1kx&amp;rdquo; powers the the OpTiMSoC compute 
tiles, and we have been active in its development for some time now. So it was 
an easy call to make when the question of where to host the next conference 
came up: visit us in Munich!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What followed was a great weekend with many interesting talks. Olof started 
off with a status update on OpenRISC in general, followed by talks presenting 
the changes to the individual components of the OpenRISC project, such as 
toolchain and various porting efforts, e.g. of the Linux Kernel. How OpenRISC 
is used in the wild was shown by reports from research groups all over Europe, 
which are using the OpenRISC architecture as base of their SoC designs. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Implementing OpenRISC in JavaScript? Why not, thought Sebastian Macke a couple 
years ago, and out of this idea the &lt;a href=&quot;http://s-macke.github.io/jor1k/&quot;&gt;jor1k&lt;/a&gt; 
emulator was born. In addition to some demos he showed us what&amp;rsquo;s necessary to 
implement a fast (80 MIPS on an iPad!) emulator in JavaScript.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The round of talks was completed by presentations of exciting 
upcoming topics such as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://riscv.org/&quot;&gt;RISC-V ISA&lt;/a&gt; with its 
implementation, &lt;a href=&quot;http://riscv.org/download.html#tab_rocket&quot;&gt;Rocket&lt;/a&gt;, the 
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.lowrisc.org/&quot;&gt;lowRISC&lt;/a&gt; project with the goal of building silicon in 
an open way, and various other topics related to free/open hardware design.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks to everybody who joined us for the conference, and thanks for making 
OpenRISC a success!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additional resources:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.flickr.com/photos/127858841@N06/sets/72157648274711327/&quot;&gt;Pictures are available on Flickr&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The presentation slides are linked from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://tum-lis.github.io/orconf2014/&quot;&gt;ORCONF 2014 website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=96MN6lhLFRY&amp;amp;list=PLOGTP9W1DX5XDdzBroA2i1ffMlCNus30M&quot;&gt;Recordings of the talks are available on YouTube.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;340&quot; src=&quot;//www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/qf-1hL6Cwhs?list=PLOGTP9W1DX5XDdzBroA2i1ffMlCNus30M&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>Sun, 12 Oct 2014 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
<link>http://www.optimsoc.org/blog/blog/2014/10/12/orconf2014.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.optimsoc.org/blog/blog/2014/10/12/orconf2014.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>Switching Host-Communication to GLIP</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;Since its beginning, OpTiMSoC contained a method for communication between a 
PC and an FPGA board. For the ZTEX 1.15 boards we used the USB 2.0 interface, 
based on the Cypress FX2 chip available on those boards. As we continued the 
development, we realized that this connectivity functionality is not only 
useful in OpTiMSoC, but in other projects as well. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We now finally got around to factor the communication interface out of OpTiMSoC 
and to moved it into a new project, which we named the &amp;ldquo;Generic Logic Interface 
Project&amp;rdquo;, or in short, GLIP. It provides generic, FIFO-based communication 
between a host and a target, abstracting away all the nitty gritty details and 
protocols in between. It lets you simply focus on the data you want to transfer, 
handling everything else for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of now GLIP contains a cleaned-up and improved version of the Cypress 
FX2-based USB 2.0 backend, reaching up to 21 MByte/s bi-directional transfer 
rate (close to the achievable maximum of the USB 2.0 interface), and a 
host-only TCP backend for communication between a simulated system (e.g. in 
ModelSim) and a controller.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the near future, other backends for JTAG and possibly PCIe are planned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We provide GLIP with an extensive set of documentation under the MIT license, 
check it out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://lis.ei.tum.de/glip/&quot;&gt;Project page and documentation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/TUM-LIS/glip&quot;&gt;Source code on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the newest latest trunk version of OpTiMSoC liboptimsochost uses GLIP for 
all Debug NoC based communications, so you need to have GLIP installed if you 
want to use those as of now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2014 20:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
<link>http://www.optimsoc.org/blog/blog/2014/07/30/glip.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.optimsoc.org/blog/blog/2014/07/30/glip.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>OpTiMSoC at FOSDEM</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s official! We are proud to announce that our talk at &lt;a href=&quot;http://fosdem.org&quot;&gt;FOSDEM&lt;/a&gt;
has been accepted. FOSDEM, for those of you who have never heard of it, is one of
the largest Free/Open Source conferences in Europe with a very strong focus on
developers and technology. It is held every year in Brusseles, Belgium. This year it
takes place on February 1st and 2nd.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we don&amp;rsquo;t expect the whole audience to be very deep into hardware design we
will first give a short introduction of how SoC design is done these days, and then
showcase some cool things you can do with OpTiMSoC. More information about the talk
is available at the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://fosdem.org/2014/schedule/event/optimisoc/&quot;&gt;conference homepage&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will be attending the whole conference, let me know if you&amp;rsquo;re around. I&amp;rsquo;d love to
hear from you if you have problems with OpTiMSoC or ideas on how to make it better.
See you at FOSDEM!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt; The nice people at FOSDEM also published a short interview with me about the
talk.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://fosdem.org/2014/interviews/2014-philipp-wagner/&quot;&gt;Find it on the FOSDEM page!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Update 2:&lt;/strong&gt; Now the recorded video is online as well.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://video.fosdem.org/2014/K1105/Sunday/OpTiMSoC.webm&quot;&gt;Download the video&lt;/a&gt;
or watch it below! The
&lt;a href=&quot;/documents/presentations/2014-fosdem-slides.pdf&quot;&gt;slides are available online&lt;/a&gt;
as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;video width=&quot;640&quot; height=&quot;480&quot;
       style=&quot;display: block; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto&quot;
       src=&quot;http://video.fosdem.org/2014/K1105/Sunday/OpTiMSoC.webm&quot; controls&gt;
  Unfortunately your browser does not support WebM video playback. Use a supported
  browser, such as Firefox or Chrome, or download the video and play it with another
  application, such as the free VLC player.
&lt;/video&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>Fri, 03 Jan 2014 11:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
<link>http://www.optimsoc.org/blog/blog/2014/01/03/fosdem.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.optimsoc.org/blog/blog/2014/01/03/fosdem.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>OpTiMSoC at ORCONF 2013</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;The &amp;ldquo;brain&amp;rdquo; in a SoC is its processor; in OpTiMSoC this task falls to a 
the freely available OpenRISC processor. For the second year now the developers
of the OpenRISC processor met in Cambridge, UK for a two-day conference on 
October 5th and 6th to discuss the current status of the project as well as
plans for the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stefan attended this conference and came home with a lot of new ideas and 
information, which we&amp;rsquo;ll incorporate into OpTiMSoC in the future. But he was
also able to give a 45 minute presentation about OpTiMSoC, what it is, and how
you can make use of it. The whole talk was recorded, you can watch it down
below or on &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gEf7EFahvAQ&quot;&gt;YouTube&lt;/a&gt;. Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;340&quot; src=&quot;http://www.youtube.com/embed/gEf7EFahvAQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2013 10:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
<link>http://www.optimsoc.org/blog/blog/2013/10/30/orconf2013.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.optimsoc.org/blog/blog/2013/10/30/orconf2013.html</guid>
</item>

<item>
<title>OpTiMSoC has a new web site!</title>
<description>&lt;p&gt;OpTiMSoC is growing rapidly. Most of the time we have our heads deep down into
the internals, chasing large and small bugs, implementing exciting new features
and if it all works, enjoy a beer at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then last weekend I thought about how we present all our work to the
public &amp;ndash; and as you might have guessed, there&amp;rsquo;s some room for improvement.
As a first step we decided to redesign our homepage, giving it more content
to help you understand what OpTiMSoC is, where you can get all the necessary
parts to get started and how you can become part of the OpTiMSoC world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We hope you like it and please get back to us with any feedback you might have.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
<pubDate>Tue, 27 Aug 2013 15:37:21 +0200</pubDate>
<link>http://www.optimsoc.org/blog/blog/2013/08/27/welcome.html</link>
<guid isPermaLink="true">http://www.optimsoc.org/blog/blog/2013/08/27/welcome.html</guid>
</item>

</channel>
</rss>
